<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title>Mithril Blog</title>
	<subtitle>A Javascript framework for building brilliant applications</subtitle>
	<id>http://lhorie.github.io/mithril-blog</id>
	<entry>
		<title>Giving Mithril a voice</title>
		<link rel="alternate" href="http://lhorie.github.io/mithril-blog/giving-mithril-a-voice.html"/>
		<content type="html"><![CDATA[
<h2 id="giving-mithril-a-voice">Giving Mithril a voice</h2>
<p><em>April 11, 2014</em></p>
<p>I released Mithril last month and the project has been getting generally positive feedback and some <a href="https://github.com/jpmonette/todomvc-mithril">good</a> <a href="https://github.com/insin/msx">traction</a>.</p>
<p>There&#39;s still a lot of things I want to share with people that aren&#39;t necessarily core Mithril features, be them interesting application developement techniques, or my own experience w/ development and even open source in general, so today I&#39;m launching this blog.</p>
<p>To give a recap of what&#39;s been happening since launch, Mithril is now a lot more accessible, being <a href="http://lhorie.github.io/mithril/installation.html">available from CDNs, and popular NodeJS package managers</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to this blog, the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/mithriljs">mailing list</a> and the <a href="https://github.com/lhorie/mithril.js/issues?state=open">Github issue tracker</a> are great places to start conversations.</p>
<p>On the plumbing end, Mithril is now on Travis CI, and the test suite is rapidly growing. It now includes regression tests for reported bugs to ensure a stable core.</p>
<p>For the next little while, I&#39;m hoping to nail down all the lingering bugs that contributors have been finding (particularly around the <code>m.render</code> method). Once I feel it&#39;s stable enough to bump Mithril to a v0.2, I&#39;ll have the chance to start putting more time on the plugin ecosystem, which has a really exciting pipeline: more readable and expressive templates, advanced optimization tools, a more wholesome approach to dependency management, etc - and hopefully no changes to the core codebase in order to support all of this :)</p>
<p>If you&#39;re liking Mithril, you can help in a few different ways. The easiest is to spread the word. Another way is to try it out and report any bugs you find. You&#39;re also welcome to post topics in the mailing list or get in touch with me directly.</p>
<p>If you want a project to take on, there&#39;s a lot of stuff that can be done in terms of plugins, and if you need help getting started, I&#39;m more than happy to help get the ball moving for you. <a href="https://github.com/lhorie/mithril.js/issues/38">This thread</a>, for example is a good starting point.</p>
<p>In the coming weeks, I&#39;m hoping to start writing more topics about actual development, both in general, and as it relates to Mithril, so stay tuned :)</p>

		]]></content>
	</entry>
</feed>